Guide to the David Mark Olds World War II Collection 1913-1978 (bulk 1940-1945) PR 287
New-York Historical Society
David Mark Olds World War II Collection
1916-1978 (bulk 1940-1945)
New-York Historical Society
PR 287
2.09 Linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains photographs and documents relating to David Mark Olds' military service during World War II. The collection includes items related to the U.S. military (such as magazines, papers, and Olds' photographs) and the German military (such as propaganda and documents for German soldiers after the surrender).
Biographical note
David Mark Olds was born in New York, NY December 29, 1920. He served in the army from 1943 to 1946, first as a Radio Intelligence Officer (1st Lieutenant), then as a Radio Officer, Field (Captain).
As a Radio Intelligence Officer, Olds translated, decoded, and intercepted enemy traffic. He served in this capacity in England, France, and Germany.
As a Radio Officer, Field, Olds was responsible for all radio circuits and installations in Austria. Headquarters were located in Vienna.
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
The N-YHS Library's collection of World War II related materials can be searched using the online catalog.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Photographs, includes photographs from Olds' time in the military.
Series II: Documents, includes Olds' military papers, European souvenirs, and periodicals.
Series III: Nazi photographs and documents, includes Nazi propaganda and documents for German soldiers after the surrender.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Provenance
Donated to the New-York Historical Society by Sally Wendkos Olds in 2011.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains photographs, documents, and other materials related to World War II, both U.S. military and Nazi items.
The U.S. military items include Olds' photographs and documents as well as periodicals. The Nazi items Olds apparently acquired while deployed. These include Nazi propaganda as well as documents created for German soldiers after Germany's surrender (directions and a safe conduct pass). In addition, the collection contains non-military items from Europe including travel souvenirs and foreign currency.
Money -- Europe, Eastern.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, American.; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.
- Series I: Photographs
  Arrangement note
  Photographs have been arranged by country. Photographs with no location or an indecipherable location written on them can be found in the "Unknown location" folder.
  - Austria, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Includes photographs from Vienna, Salzburg, the Brenner Pass, and other locations. Most photographs appear to be from Olds, except one 1916 photograph of "Members of the Radio Sub/Committee for Austria."
  - France, 1944, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes photographs from Strasbourg, Reims, Camp Oklahoma City (near Reims), and other locations.
  - Germany, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains photographs from Bavaria (including Munich, Berchtesgaden, and Rosenheim), and other locations. Includes photographs of German prisoners of war and U.S. soldiers sorting loot. Herrenchiemsee Palace is labeled as "King Ludwig's Palace/Castle."
  - Other European countries, 1944, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes photographs from Belgium, England, Italy, and Switzerland. The Château de Chillon is located in Switzerland.
  - United States, 1943, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains photographs from Fort Dix and Washington, D.C.
  - United States, 1943, 1947, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains photographs from New Jersey, Washington, D.C., and possibly New York.
  - Unknown location, 1942, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes photographs from various unknown locations, primarily of men in uniform or photographs of women (most signed).
- Series II: Documents
  - Olds military papers, 1943, 1946, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains "Journal of the 3255 Signal Service Company in Europe 44/45," soldier orientation documents, military separation records, military course certificate, and presidential memorial certificate.
  - Letter from Olds to his family, published in Lines of Battle, Letters from American Servicement 1941-1945 (photocopy), 1945 July 12 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Soldier's Handbook, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Souvenirs, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes postcards, a booklet about Berchtesgaden, and a handmade dictionary.
  - Money, 1920, 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    Contains German marks, German banknotes, and Czechoslovak koruna.
  - Periodicals, 1945-1978 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Contains three issues of Yank magazine and a historical newspaper article about the Holocaust.
  - Photocopies of excerpts from a glossary, chapter, and map, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Series III: Nazi photographs and documents
  - Documents for German soldiers after surrender, unknown (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains directions for surrendering soldiers and a safe conduct pass.
  - Book by Heinrich Hoffmann, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Mit Hitler im Westen published in 1940.
  - Nazi propaganda and other documents, 1938-1943, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes miniature Hitler Propaganda booklets, miniature government-published song and folktale booklets, German army propaganda postcards, a Hitler postcard, and a map of troop movements.
  - Nazi documents, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains a blank certificate with the printed signature of Heinrich Himmler and a map of troop movements.